hey guys bre and teras here uh today's
topic is on back pain and uh this is
something that uh I think deserves more
attention from strength coaches I've
heard a lot of physical therapists talk
about it but I don't think I've heard
any strength coaches really do it
justice so um hope you pay close
attention because again this is a a
topic that will improve uh your ability
to help your clients so uh specifically
I want to talk about two different
models with with back page
the first is uh the PSB model and PSB
stands for postural structural
biomechanical model and uh the second
model is the the BPS Model or the bioc
psychosocial
model so um I'm going to start off with
the PSB model so um the postural
structural biomechanical model um it
dictates that the things that cause pain
um would be related to the things that
cause back pain would be related to um
you know posture structure and
biomechanics so I will explain this
um uh you could uh under this model you
could analyze somebody's um Anatomy for
example you could look at their their
posture and positions you could look at
uh their form and how they move and then
you could determine by this you know why
they are stressing a certain part
uh a certain you know part of the body a
certain part of the spine too much and
that's why you are causing mechanical
low back
pain um I will say that uh based on what
I've seen uh I feel that uh physical
therapists need to give this model more
concern uh a lot of uh the physical
therapists in the last couple of years
have uh completely drifted away from
this model to the biopsychosocial model
saying that uh you know chronic back
pain well saying that back pain has
nothing to do with posture biomechanics
or structure it only has to do with uh
the nervous system and the the
biopsychosocial model and um if that's
the way you think then you're missing
the boat because the the PSB model came
first uh and and it's there for good
reason it's uh it it if you're a
strength coach if you're a personal
trainer um you know you've seen this
happen over and over if you don't
believe it just you know stand up and
Arch the hell out of your lower back for
five minutes do it with you know heavy
weight do it over and over for one day
do 20 sets of back extensions or
deadlifts while hyperextending or round
your back do a bunch of round back
deadlifts with heavy weight and see how
you feel the next day and then tell me
that uh that that biomechanics has
nothing to do with low back pain anyone
who says that is uh is absurd they're
they're just um they don't get it they
don't understand what they're talking
about so uh I'm going to talk about this
model for a few minutes and then drift
over to the other
model so this model applies better to
athletes and to weightlifters and it
applies more to acute pain it does not
apply as much to chronic pain so and
that's very important to understand here
uh chronic pain is more related to the
biopsychosocial model and acute pain you
know ah I'm lifting weights and I feel a
sharp pain in my back something went
wrong well that's probably due to
biomechanics and posture and
structure um and again obviously
athletes and people exercising and
people lifting heavy weights you know
when you're holding on to a weight or
putting a weight on your back you are
now and you're lifting weights through
that a full range of motion like
squatting and deadlifting you need this
core stability if your spine Wiggles
around under heavy load you're going to
increase the chance of of injury so of
pain and injury so uh I will break down
the three mechanisms in this model uh
posture structure and biomechanics so
the first um is uh structure and anatomy
and this looks at your you know your
skeletal structure the size of your you
know the size and shape of your bones uh
um you know your uh
anthropometry your uh your discs your
vertebrae um your uh sacral you know
sacral slope the your pelvis and all
these different measures of anatomy and
Studies have shown that uh that your
chance of getting an injury a low back
injury is related to posture if you have
certain like a um an anterior uh like a
a very steep sacral slope you are going
to have more sheer force on that L5 S1
um
but I will tell you a lot of studies
show that like pelvic tilt and different
mechanical factors are not related to
chronic pain well I will tell you in the
weight room this does matter uh people
who have anterior pelvic tilt or lumbar
hyperlordosis they do have much higher
incidences of feeling their low back
hurt with certain exercises and
conversely people who have posterior
pelvic tilt and Lumbar hypolordosis have
increased uh risk of experiencing pain
and injury in certain exercises I'll
deal with that in a second but posture
uh relates to the different positions
you know your posture when you squat you
know are you how how how arched are you
do you round over um posture is you know
do what kind of positions do you sleep
in uh do you sit all day long you know
the positions you get yourself in
throughout the day structure is anatomy
but it's not just the skeletal structure
it's also you know the muscles and where
they insert uh Origins and insertions
and um strength balances things like
that um and your your uh biomechanics
would also be influenced by your
strength balances so you want you know
in general you want the muscles on the
front side of the body to be uh as
strong as the muscles on the back side
of the body you want balance in there
depending on the exercise some muscles
get activated higher than the others but
you want a balance um for example if you
uh if your lumbar you know if your
Erectors are very strong and your hip
extensors are not very strong then
you're chances are you're going to want
to to uh you know pick things off the
floor deadlift or or uh do good mornings
or or even squats you're going to want
to use your back more you're going to
want to use those muscles dynamically so
um this all influences your likelihood
of experiencing pain um so uh for
example if you uh I I'll talk about the
knee for a second if you are squatting
you know and your knees cave in as you
come up your knees cave in uh while
you're squatting this uh will um you
know put more pressure on the lateral
sides of the knee and you have a greater
chance of experiencing patellofemoral
pain so in that sense uh biomechanics
influences the likelihood of pain and
injury uh with the lumbar spine um let's
say you are um hypolordotic you have an
excessive curvature of the lumbar spine
it's arched too much you have anterior
pelvic tilt excessive anterior pelvic
tilt um and you are doing a back
extension or a hip thrust and as you
come up in the hip thrust or as you you
know hold the weight and rise up in a
back
extension if you uh your Anatomy is
already those posterior elements of the
spine are already closer together
they're already kind of jammed closer
together and so now if you are the type
who uses your you know moves into even
greater
hyperextension or you relies too much on
your Erectors say you don't have strong
glutes you don't know how to you know
control pelvic tilt and you want to rely
on your hamstrings more you will tilt
the pelvis more forward into Anor tilt
and you will Arch the back even harder
as you come up and you will Jam those
facets together the facet joints and you
have a higher likelihood of experiencing
pain and injury so in that sense uh
Anatomy you know posture and
biomechanics definitely plays a role in
injury and on the flip side let's say
you were in posterior pelvic tilt uh you
have a flattened lumbar spine it's
hypolordotic
um and you know you kind of have no
glutes you don't how you don't know how
to activate them well and the these
types of people typically will round
over they they want to round with
everything and just use their spine
dynamically to lift things up so you
give them a deadlift and they will round
over and pick the weight up they are
using their hip extensors
statically and their Erectors
dynamically and they will have increased
uh chance of herni herting a disc and
getting back pain from deadlifts because
they will want to round so um you know
as you can see there are a lot of
examples another one is sleeping uh you
sleep in an awkward position you know
you're it's going to hurt the next day
uh do again like I said earlier do a
heavy round back deadlift and you know
let your form slip too much without
controlling that Lumar spine you are
going to feel it um so uh in lifting
there's often a biomechanical
explanation for this pain and so usually
people's backs hurt due to excessive
motion during lifting and so we talk
about core stability this does not mean
that the spine doesn't move it just
means that we prevent excessive motion
and too much motion and not enough you
know strength at the hips and things
like that and you increase your chances
of injury so that's the B the postural
structural biomechanical
model it is very plausible with
weightlifting and sports um and
typically what we do is we you know go
through the process of teaching somebody
how to be a good lifter we will give
them for example hip mobility drills to
increase their hip mobility we we'll
give them core stability drills to
increase their core stability glute
activation drills to get their glutes
activating better and you know motor
control exercise will really stress good
form with light loads so we might give
them you know soas stretches rectus Fus
stretches hip internal rotation
stretches um walking knee hugs different
types of lunges um planks side planks p
off presses glute Bridges sideline clams
sideline abductions um you know hip
hinging drills box squats with
lightweight goblet squats things like
this and get them using very good form
get their knees tracking over their toes
get them hinging at the hips keeping the
core stable get them feeling the glutes
working and voila this works miracles
for a lot of people you know people who
always said oh I can't do squats I can't
do deadlifts I can't do this exercise
because it hurts my back all of a sudden
they are are you know performing these
movements painfree and you know they
they love you to death as their coach
because you just you know taught them
how to lift without hurting their back
so that is the postural structural
biomechanical model uh and it it is very
important for uh for people who work
with people in back pain uh be it manual
therapists or physical therapists or uh
strength coaches personal trainers
athletic trainers trainers um doctors um
they need to understand this model
because it's very very important it's uh
it's there it's the very important model
for a good reason however if this is all
you know you are only aware of the
postural structural biomechanical model
you and then you know all you have is a
hammer everything looks like a nail so I
will tell you in my own personal
experience as a personal trainer this
this is all I used to know about and so
everyone who came to me and said Brett
my knee hurts or my back hurts I just
thought oh you know it's because they
they have crappy form and you know they
they're weak in certain areas or tight
in other areas and they need to give
specific they need to receive specific
corrective exercise stretches and
strengthening exercises and then it'll
fix their form up and their pain will go
away well and and sometimes I was
probably fooled because pain tends to go
away anyway on its own so I thought I
probably thought oh I fixed them and
this does not work with everyone first
of all it doesn't work with people in
chronic pain well it it actually can
work and it can be very effective but
for reasons other than what you're
thinking U I'll get to that in a minute
but it also doesn't work for people with
who need for example who need surgical
interventions who have serious issues
wrong with them you know it's not always
strength related or flexibility related
or motor control related sometimes
there's an issue that requires you know
uh a surgical intervention or a
different approach and the solution is
not just exercising um I will say that
uh studies show that bed rest is not
good for back pain you don't just want
to lay around all day long you do want
to be moving moving movement is often
the solution but not always for the
reasons why people think so this leads
me to the next model the biopsychosocial
model um now this model is uh is very
important to understand uh strength
coaches need to give this model more
concern they need to understand this um
and this applies more to to people in
chronic pain more to more to sedentary
folks um who aren't exercising all the
time um and you know chronic pain pain
that's been there for a while uh it's
not just due to biomechanics it's it's
it's more due to things like biology
psychology and
sociology hence the biopsychosocial
model so let me explain this if you were
to look at uh if you were to take you
know a 100 people and you know some of
the people are in pain some of the
people are not in pain you were to take
MRIs of all those people and you were to
look at different joints you were to
look at the knee joint the um you know
the the the lumbar discs and different
joints shoulder joint you would see
evidence of degeneration in almost
everyone in fact studies show that
there's evidence of disc degeneration at
age two uh it's just a natural
consequence of living you know we
degenerate over time and so a lot of
these you know very eye-opening um you
know Studies have been performed where
they look at these MRIs of a large
number of people and they can see that
it's not you know pain and injury is not
um well pain is not highly related to
biomechanics and anatomy and things like
that or to damage to degeneration you
will see a lot of people who have you
know a degenerate disc you know two de
degenerate discs and they ex they
exhibit no pain whatsoever they're
asymptomatic and conversely you can have
somebody who's in severe pain who
doesn't you know you look at their MRI
and it there's no explanation why they
should have pain because it looks
normal and so uh you know things like
posture and biome mechanics and
structure are not highly highly
correlated with chronic pain um most of
us are jacked up at most of our joints I
mean you sitting there listening to me
right now ramble you probably have
degeneration throughout your body and uh
you probably don't feel it and there's a
reason why so if all you know if you
just think of pain as like oh I I punch
my knee ow it hurts um that's not you
know this this pain signal it will
travel from your knee up to your brain
but your brain has to make a decision as
to whether to send a signal back down to
that spot and elicit a pain response
so
um the brain in chronic pain they're
always sending that pain signal it
doesn't shut down and and chronic pain
has been shown to be uh correlated with
things like depression
uh number of friends and support group
and confidence and things like that so
how do you deal with the chronic pain uh
you know person well the first step in
my opinion is is teaching them you know
knowledge is the first step they need to
be aware that they are not destined to
have back pain for life they can
overcome it and it starts off with
knowing and believing that you can
overcome it um you know first of all
damage can heal herniations are are in a
state of flux they can heal um uh they
don't you get biomechanically inferior
healing but you you you know they are in
a state of flux they will improve a
little bit um and biomechanics can
improve too so your form and things like
that through strengthening but it's not
necessarily let's say you you have
somebody lifting weights and getting
stronger it's not necessary that they're
improving their biom mechanics or their
form um or or let's say you're using
manual therapy you know massage and and
techniques and things like that um and
all these different there's a ton of
different techniques um that have become
popular over the last you know decade
they they don't always work for the
reasons expected you know uh art was the
first thing that really got popular you
know since I've been around in the
strength and conditioning industry and
art proposed that you are you know you
know you're targeting trigger points and
getting the trigger points to settle
down you are breaking up adhesions and
Scar Tissue um and uh this is not all
you know sometimes you can do art on
someone and it might relieve their pain
but it's not because of those reasons a
lot of people have really um glamorized
fascia in the last decade and they feel
that fascia has these magical properties
and that that's the secret to Chon you
know healing chronic pain and it's
probably not related to the fascia
either it's probably not related to any
tissue other than the ner tissue related
to the nervous system you know the
nerves and the brain and the pain is a
nerve and brain uh phenomenon and so
when you heal people's chronic pain when
you get them out of chronic pain you are
uh you are essentially teaching their
brain uh to not elicit that pain
response and so
all these things that people do that
have been
successful can work movement uh manual
therapy things like thatt but it's
because of different reasons that you
are altering the brain's perceptions and
the nervous systems response um and so
when you do you know let's say I get a
client and you know they tell me that
they can't do certain exercise because
they have back pain and it hurts well
what I will do you know hopefully theyve
been to phys physical therapist and
things like that I don't just take on
any client but what I would do is just
try to see what can I give them that's
painfree can I give them a really high
box squat can I give them a you know a
hip hinging movement with short range of
motion can I give them glute Bridges
Maybe feet elevated glute Bridges maybe
I have to use bands and cables to assist
them you know so they're only lifting a
percentage of their body weight but I
get them to do things that they can do
and this also applies to the manual
therapist and people who are doing
things and what this does is it
increases their confidence it increases
their it decreases their the threat the
fear you know a lot of this pain is due
to fear and this threat of movement and
you're essentially teaching their body
it's okay to go through this range of
motion and little by little you chip
away at this and they increase their
range of motion and they increase their
their strength and their loading and all
the while they've got a good personal
train trainer or a massage therapist or
strength coach who cares about them they
feel that love there they know that
they've got a a a trainer who cares
about them they are confident in their
trainer they believe in the trainer the
trainer Praises them Pats them on the
back and little by little this helps
because it increases their confidence it
decreases that that that threat response
that fear and little by little they
learn to override their you know that
that signal and now the brain doesn't
keep sending that signal down to elicit
chronic pain and so again movement May
might be a solution for either model but
you need to be aware of this because
um uh they need to understand that you
know it's it's it takes time if it took
you a lot of years to get into this pain
and the pain could have started from a
biomechanical reason you know maybe you
herniated a dis a disc doing deadlifts
and then just never rehabilitated never
got over it and your brain just learned
to be very afraid of this and to keep
that signal ke kept
persisting and uh I think this explains
why you know all serious lifters hurt
themselves several times throughout the
year and we can get pretty bad injuries
and then we're up we're uplifting
training around it a few days later and
and you know if you've been through this
before you kind of know I just need to
be smart and not be stupid and I will be
okay and there have been many lifters
who have come back from you know
debilitating injuries to set new levels
of strength records and things like that
so um I hope you've enjoyed this video
again it's an important it's important
to understand both models uh if you want
to look more into it you could type into
uh uh Google you know the the
biopsychosocial model and the um the
postural structural biomechanical model
and you will get links that you can read
um there was a a man named anop Bandon
who wrote an excellent blog post uh for
me a guest blog post on my blog a couple
years back pertaining to pain and
chronic pain um there is a website uh
Somas simple
do.com uh s o m s i
m.com where they teach people a lot
about uh pain and how it's related to
the nervous system
and Stu McGill uh a a professor in
Canada a spinal biomechanist has
published lots of papers on you know
biomechanics of low back pain and things
like that he's written two books as well
so these are all resources you could
check out if you're interested in this
topic but uh again therapists uh coaches
personal trainers athletic trainers um
doctors who work with this type of
people need to understand both models
and how they how they jive together so
again hope you like the video thanks for
watching